[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome to the stoa uh my name is jared
uh i'm the kind of stand-in steward uh
for for this session um and uh
and yeah just a quick thanks to peter
for for making this uh what is what is
the stoa line is it uh this is a place
for us to cohere
around dialogue i don't know i can't
remember i'm a failure i'm a
terrible steward in the store so but uh
anyways um so yeah
today we're going to be talking a bit
about vadriana and things and so i'll
just hand things
over to charlie and uh we can get
started here
thanks jared hello everybody welcome to
evolving ground at the stower
my name is charlie aubry i'm co-hosting
with jared
i'm also known by the tibetan name
rinsing palmer
i write at vadriananow.com
this is the first session of a
foundational series in which we're going
to draw on the methods and principles of
vajrayana buddhism to inform an approach
to contemporary life and practice
and so vadriana means literally the path
of the vajra
the vadrapath avatara is a ritual
weapon symbolizing indestructible
force
that's this is avadra it's a little one
you can get some very big ones so
vadriana
is eventually about learning how to
appropriately
access and harness the raw power
of your personal emotional
mental social circumstances
in order to engage in useful creative
activity that benefits other people
vajrayana's it's quite a late
development in buddhism
developed roughly around the 6th century
in india and a couple of centuries after
that it spread into tibet
it also developed distinct branches in
japan
and in some parts of southeast asia
vatriana comprises several fields or
domains of practice you might say it
includes buddhist
tantra which is quite distinct from
hindu tantra
there are many crossovers historically
it also includes
zog chan and it includes mahamudra
these are all terms that you may have
come across in the buddhist sphere
so what all these fields of practice
have in common
is that they're characterized by an
attitude towards
physical emotional mental social
experience that is
non-renunciative adriana's methodology
draws on
involvement in actively
engaging with desires with attachments
with emotions and circumstances
so it's very different from some other
forms of buddhism
but as tantra employs the principle of
transformation
and transformation requires engagement
it requires involvement
job chen and mahamudra work on the
principle of integration
and liberation you can't integrate
without engaging so
all of adriana is it's defined by
the employment of non-renunciative
methodology
that's what distinguishes it from other
sorts of buddhism
so a little bit about myself i have a
background in traditional
vajrayana practice i was an apprentice
in the yarrow tale lineage
of the tibetan myanmar school
many years i took tantric vows in
2002 so
i practiced vajrayana in a traditional
setting for more than 20 years
and then about i guess 18 months ago
i gave up adherence to the ordination
vows in the traditional form that they
take
and i moved away from that traditional
practice
setting it's a little bit about my
background
um jared and i
got together about a year ago um
we were discussing practice and
meditation in relation to vajrayana
practice and evolving ground came about
as a result
of our discussions over the last year
about
adriana's view and employing the
principles of adriana in contemporary
form so
maybe you could introduce yourself jared
say a little bit about yourself yeah
yeah um
so yeah my name is jared janes um i
have been um i guess
a serious meditator for around six or
seven years
um i started out in the kind of
pragmatic dharma scene
and spent a lot of time um with uh
unified mindfulness which comes from
shinzen young and
um and then also a fair bit of amount of
time in uh
the mind illuminated by juliudasa which
is kind of a
um a little bit more of a
shamatha concentration path um and uh
it always kind of felt a little bit like
an outsider
i couldn't really sign up i felt like a
tourist um and uh
uh ran into charlie's blog because she
was
talking about um the difference between
uh shamatha
which is a similar practice but from the
adriana view and so it's kind of
radically different in some ways
um and so uh you know over the the past
year we've
kind of moved into more vajrayana
practice and and stances and perspective
and
just kind of overall disposition uh and
and kind of
finally found like i was like oh this is
this is where i belong i guess um
and uh and yeah we wanted to kind of
share it and we did one of these stoa
sessions
um about a month or two ago i believe
thinking like maybe a few random yogi's
would show up and
uh ended up being a lot more interest
than we thought so it seemed like this
was the right time to
to try and uh uh you know do something a
little bit crazy
um so i wanted to give a quick
little outline on on the plan for today
uh and then hand things back
to charlie to uh talk about
you know kind of the main presentation
today which is going to be on method
um and um
so yeah so basically we'll have a quick
presentation
charlie and i will we'll talk a little
bit about uh those concepts
then we'll do some q a uh and then we'll
move into
uh breakout sessions uh for each
individual to some
individual groups to be able to kind of
relate and and have some
more personal stuff and then we'll uh
regroup uh as
uh um as we wrap things up uh and i
think we'll also after we stop recording
um we'll probably stick around for a bit
uh if there's some lingering questions
or things
um so so yeah feel free to stick around
a bit afterwards uh if that sounds like
something that's interesting to you
i think that's it let me let me look at
my we we're trying to be a little bit
more organized last time we were
kind of flying by the city yeah it was
kind of spontaneous yeah
yeah so we're we have a plan today
um yeah charlie you want to start right
so
yeah i'll say a little bit about what
we're intending
and what we're doing here um
so yeah our intentions are to create
the space for a community of knowledge
and practice that's informed by
vajrayana so really for people who want
to live
with the views and with the principles
and methods
the functions that were all developed in
the traditional vajrayana lineages but
without
the cultural worldview that generated
them
and with newly adaptive forms
that are fitting for contemporary
experience
so vadriana forms the base
the root for this series evolving ground
traditional vadriana is the ground from
which we're evolving if you like
um so in particular we're working with
principle
and function in vadriana method and
path and so all the way through the
series we're going to be coming back to
that theme
we'll be exploring what that means and
how to employ vajrayana method
in different contexts so this isn't a
rejection
i want to make that very clear this
isn't a rejection for
something new it's the offering of
something new
as well that is very much grounded
in a history and in a
lineage that has a certain kind of
coherence to it
so it really should be possible for
anybody practicing in this community to
move
into a more traditional setting and a
more traditional world view without
experiencing
some great sort of conflict in principle
or some kind of contradiction there
that shouldn't happen and vice versa it
also ought to be possible for people to
move
from traditional settings to
practice with evolving ground and
actually have some sort of sense of
familiarity and recognition
so what i'm saying is that if if you
understand how a practice method works
in terms of its principle and
in terms of its function then
that that's translatable into lots of
different contexts
so the um
the the principle and what it's supposed
to do
um and the the the
context are all the sort of key elements
here that
make it possible to move between
different environments
with similar sorts of practices so this
first
series comprises the ground or the base
from which all kinds of forms new forms
might arise
but the material presented is hopefully
it's going to be like the 101
for the system that we're building
and so as such it's also the link it's
like a link in a chain
back to traditional vajrayana practice
so what i want to say about that is that
the
the more involved you become in any kind
of system of practice the more
informative it can be to understand the
history
and the roots of that practice or the
tradition of knowledge tradition of
knowledge if you like
and it can save a lot of time it can cut
through incoherence
so once you start having a feel for a
system
and its practices how they might
function in your life
understanding how they were generated
and what gave rise to them
i'm talking socially and politically
here as well
it's very good at some point to get a
much rounder
fuller sense of the context of the
practice the historical context of the
practice rather than
what you might call an aesthetic
understanding this applies across all
domains i think
so you begin to get a much better sense
of how and why
a particular mode or method functions in
the way that it does
and in doing so you're better able to
predict how something's likely to pan
out
what the different outcomes might be
from following
specific modes of practice for example
i should say something about principle
and function so jared and i
use the terms principle and function
frequently
principle is how something works and a
function
is what it does kettle
employs the principle of transforming
electricity into heat and its function
is to boil water
tap employees the principle that
manually turning a screw lifts a washer
and then its function is to regulate the
flow of water
chud zavadriana practice it employs the
principle
of cutting through the habitual
relationship
to corporeal form our habitual
um the way that we are with
physical reality and its function is to
induce an experience
in which death and life are understood
as
inseparable or you know that's one way
of putting it different ways of putting
it
so it's very good when you're practicing
or when you're meditating
um with anything really it's very good
to have some kind
of understanding at least of the
function of the activity
that you're engaged with what it's
supposed to do
where it's supposed to lead and if you
get into the habit
of figuring out and understanding the
principle
and understanding the function of your
activity
then that can help bring some coherence
into
navigating your way through all the
different
practices and cultural views and
different histories that are available
so i think i'll talk
about method which is the topic
of today's session
so each each session in this
foundational series we're going to take
one topic
today's topic is method and what do i
mean
method um
it's quite probable that i'm going to
slow down
sometimes because i really want to use
language quite carefully
and i want to be clear about what i mean
and you know i think we have
a kind of tendency in buddhist circles
to use phrases that have become a bit
cliched maybe a little bit you know
they're very widely used
so what that leads to is a lot of
ambiguity or a lot of fuzziness
um around meaning
sometimes you know this kind of
particular cliche or phrase use you
um if you if you stop to notice what's
going on
you can kind of get the feeling that the
function of a word or a phrase is not
in keeping with what it purports to be
like it purports to point to something
special or something different or
non-ordinary but the actual function in
context
is it's just to give a feel-good vibe or
you know
or something or signal authority or
something like that
so i think i think it's really useful to
notice how
words function um
socially somatically
you know how is the use of certain words
affecting your sensibility
what function does the particular
language that some guru or some
authority is using what what function
does that
seem to serve i'm kind of getting
tangential here and i
was supposed to be talking about method
so anyway yeah i think some
words have been horribly abused in that
they've
they've come to sort of be ways to
manipulate people's hopes and
desires if you know what i mean they
sort of
subtly manipulate promise and i think
that happens a lot
in spiritual circles reality
the word reality is a word that's been
it's gotten abused
in this way
so anyway i think what i'm saying is
that i don't want to do that
with words and language but because of
that it means being very conscientious
maybe a little laborious so i might need
to just kind of stop
and think sometimes um about
what i'm saying and how i'm saying it
so anyway method method
so i want to say something about
how i see method as being different
to tool
these they're nouns they're
somewhat distinct i'm using the word
method in a very particular way
so a tool is a thing with which you
apply a technique
think of some some literal examples you
have a wrench you fit the wrench to a
bolt head you apply some force
you turn the nut it's very precise
not a lot of wiggle room there your
wrench is like is like a certain
size it's going to be quite um
defined it's you know it's a sort of
very adapted for a particular specific
use
you fit the nut you turn it you you
could apply this
wrench in many contexts
um in british that's a spanner for the
brits
now so it's pretty much always going to
be
the same motion it's going to be the
same technique so a clue
a tool a tool is a clearly defined
object
for our purposes the way that i'm using
that word it's pretty obvious what a
wrench
is it looks like a wrench it works like
a wrench it's a wrench right
she couldn't mistake it for a duck or
it doesn't quack like a duck the
technique is like
very precise so a technique
how does a technique work it
it's like you can hone your technique
you you can make it more refined
you can the way that you become familiar
with the technique is that you get even
less wiggle room
it's it's really precise it's ever more
refined
so you think about meditation as a tool
that's what you've got you've got a tool
you apply your technique that's going to
be very clear
and precise as well so
examples of meditation techniques are
like focusing on the breath
concentrate on the breath as object
ignore
the thought there's a little bit of
wiggle room there
not a lot there's a little bit you can
like do you focus on the in-breath or
the out breath or the all
all of the breath but it's really quite
honed
and it's like you practice in order to
further refine
that technique that's how your practice
develops
you narrow in on the sensation at the
tip of the nose
um or something like that you know it's
it's ever more refined it's ever more
concentrated even less wiggle room
that's how tools and techniques work
your meditation can be a tool with which
you
apply a technique so
now let's think about method a method
is not a tool a method in the way that
i'm using this term
is a way it's a way to employ
a principle so i was thinking about this
i
came up with this um analogy
um a sort of very literal analogy which
is paddling
paddling being the principal so i mean
paddling like you're doing a
canoe not paddling in a puddle that sort
of paddling
you you use a paddle so if you're in
your canoe and you're paddling in white
water down some rapids you're going to
be using the paddle in a very certain
way
you know it might be quite frenetic or
maybe it's quite a light touch but it's
all pretty chaotic
it's unpredictable there you are like
paddling away
frantically trying to stay upright in
the water
and you're employing the paddling
principle that's an aspect of what
you're doing there in order to
navigate your way through the white
water
so there you are paddling
if you are
canoeing across a very still lake
you know the paddling you're still
paddling but the paddling is going to
feel
very different still paddling
still paddling because the principle is
the same you're using a flat
board at the end of a stick to generate
the force to
guide a vessel
maybe there's a little bit more
precision possible when you're paddling
on the lake but there's a lot of wiggle
room right
there's a lot you can paddle very deep
and you can move forward quite fast or
you can use the power to kind of
to steer the vehicle in one way or
another you can go any which way you
want
you can you can go backwards you're
still paddling
so as a principal paddling is highly
adaptable
doesn't have to be a very precise fit
it's uh you know it's it's not
like a wrench which is of a very
particular size and
very particular application it's really
quite different
and you can really you can change your
method and employ the principle of
paddling
you use a kayak not a canoe
you've got a different sort of a paddle
but you know the experience changes
again
still paddling
you take like one of those uh precarious
board things that people stand up on
and uh again very long sort of paddle
thing and you're moving yourself around
um on the water and still paddling
paddling still paddling
it's quite different same principle
different method so
where are we going with this so take a
little moment now
maybe think about the difference between
these two analogies
and how they're distinct and how they
reflect the difference between
tools that apply techniques methods that
operate according to principles
like you know analogies are never
perfect but there's a distinction here
that i'm pointing to
the distinction between different ways
of practicing different ways of
meditating different ways
of relating to life circumstances
so
when when meditation is your tool you
you're applying your
precision technique maybe that's focus
or maybe it's concentration of some sort
when meditation is your method
you're employing your principle
so supposing supposing the principle
that you're going to employ
in your meditation is um remaining
uninvolved remaining uninvolved
so let's think about that if you're very
sleepy
your eyes want to close your brain brain
is kind of you've got brain fog and
you're sort of drowsy
remaining uninvolved that's
maintaining conscious aware
presence remains on remaining
uninvolved with the sleepy experience
that's the practice
of remaining uninvolved it's going to
feel a certain way
it's going to have a certain sort of
quality certain sort of texture
to it and it's going to be defined
somewhat by a sort of sleepiness and a
sort of slight sort of tension with
sleepiness isn't it
and then the practice at that point is
defined by the experience of remaining
uninvolved with
sleepiness so by contrast you can
you know if you if you've got a very
different sort of meditation experience
if you say for example you can't stop
thinking about the film that you were
watching
last night the remaining uninvolved
practice is going to be maintaining
presence by remaining uninvolved with
the film story with the visuals with the
memories with the
you know all of that activity that's
going on it's going to feel
very different to remaining uninvolved
with sleepiness
the way you even employ that principle
might be quite different
so you know another example like if
you're experiencing little itchies and
little spiders walking all over you
that practice of maintaining conscious
presence and awareness without involving
the sensation of the
the you know without getting all
involved in that sensation
and wanting to do something about it you
know that's again it's very different
very different indeed so um
the difference here between meditation
as your tool
and meditation as your method like you
know when it's your tool
it really doesn't matter what else is
going on you apply the technique
and it's always the same technique
that's the whole point
like everything else is a distraction
you apply that technique
and you further refine the the technique
you
you don't stop focusing on the breath
you maintain your concentration you're
keeping it the same
when so when when meditation is your
method you're employing a principle you
say you're employing this principle of
remaining uninvolved
the experience is shaped by that context
of uninvolvement so the context
the environment within which you're
employing that principle
shapes the experience of what it is like
to employ the the principle doesn't
always mean the same thing
it's still the same principle like still
paddling still remaining uninvolved
paddling adapting to context shaped by
the context
using a spanner it's always the same
motion it's always going to be
the same thing like righty-tighty
lefty-loosey is the thing isn't it it's
like it's always
the same focusing you just get better at
it
keep doing the same thing
so that is a way in which shine
meditation
remaining uninvolved is quite distinct
and quite different
to the way that we're using these terms
shamatha and
focusing and concentration shine is
highly nebulous
by comparison it's really so much wiggle
room
there so that makes it
not quite so easy to put your finger on
what you're supposed to be doing
because you're what you're doing is
employing a principle
not applying a technique so you can't
you can't do that automatically it can
only ever be intelligent right
you can't get into this you're still
doing the same thing and there's a sort
of gradation
and that's why it's very easy to lose
the practice
when when you're practicing chine it's
really easy to you know that's just
going to keep happening you're going to
keep losing it
you're going to keep losing it it's
it's kind of different to focus and
concentration
and you know focus concentration
that um that technique can be kind of
graduated in a way that
is less easy to do with remaining
uninvolved
and you can have you know when you're
when you're using focusing technique you
can kind of
have a less sharp focus somehow and then
get better
at the focus becoming more sharp and
sort of more
keen like that sort of precision tooling
analogy you just can't do that with
remaining uninvolved not so much anyway
it's
um it's less graduated you tend to fall
into involvement
and then find on involvement again
that's kind of how it works
and then you know the the periods of
uninvolvement with
whatever it is they start to
to lengthen once you become more
familiar and more
adept at applying or
employing that that principle
okay so so meditation
meditation is an example of
a method it's just it's one particular
method
that can employ a principle and
remaining uninvolved that was an example
of a principle
but because it's a principle and not a
technique
like with paddling like with the you
know paddling with the canoes all the
different canoes
all sorts of method can employ that
principle
and this can get broader and broader it
can become quite nebulous
so you can get to the point where you
say it's the context that is the method
that defines the principle if that isn't
a little bit too
convoluted you can remain uninvolved
you remain uninvolved when someone's
wrong on the internet
you can remain uninvolved when someone's
you know attempting to coerce you into
behaving in a particular way or you know
trying to
make you do or say something that they
want you to say
you can remain uninvolved when anger is
arising
the definition is maintaining conscious
presence
it's like the definition is
is awareness of the whole situation
without involvement that's all
that's employing the principle so
going back to the technique yeah
technique is really exclusive it's
distinct
it's precise and you know some somewhat
conceptually abstract
as well it can look and be the same in
any kind of context whereas employing a
principle is really context
dependent so that's another important
difference i think between
the principle of remaining uninvolved
and the technique of
focusing remaining uninvolved it means
that the choice
the option for involvement is always
present
remaining uninvolved it's not separate
from involvement
it's defined by knowing and seeing and
feeling
the possibility for involvement that's
always there
it's always there so the more
that you get used to that it's like the
easier that
option becomes eventually it's just a
choice it's like
there's no pull in the direction of
involvement
although the possibility of involvement
is
still always present
so that's um that's like an example of a
principle and how the context
the context which is the method shapes
the principle
so if meditation is your method
you can employ the principle of
remaining uninvolved with whatever
arises
and then once you get quite familiar and
you get quite comfortable
with that it becomes possible to employ
other
different principles but um you know in
in vajrayana practice a lot of them
really do rely on this familiarity with
remaining uninvolved
and methods and principles kind of go
hand in hand as well it's like
i've said that the context defines how
the principle manifests
like what it you know what the what that
texture is like what it looks and feels
like
remaining uninvolved with thought
stories you know it's kind of different
to remaining uninvolved with sleepiness
and the the principle defines the method
to some extent they're
they're sort of inseparable in context
you you know you
you don't take a paddle up on a mountain
hike it's kind of it would be
incongruent
to employ paddling while you're hiking
just like you know it's
it would be incongruent to employ
renunciation of attraction
and and desire when you're engaging in a
romantic relationship with somebody it
would be a misapplication
of principle
so yeah maybe i've uh
how long have i been going on for a
while yeah
um yeah i i was kind of as you're
talking about this
well you know the first reflection that
came up is because we're talking about
the specifics of
of practice um and uh
getting used to shine because coming
from this concentration for
place uh you know many of the sits are
very
very similar uh they you know you're
always trying to
recreate the same experience
in some way um and uh and and the more
that i've gotten comfortable
practicing shine the more i'm like
really interested like so on our we have
a slack channel and we always do the we
do uh
some some people practice uh we have
this little practice log where we
give a little update on you know how our
how our meditation went for the day
uh and the first thing i always write is
the environment that i was in
because that is kind of the that's the
context that defines
so much of the quality of that sit right
um
as before it was always like the the
context was more of a
hindrance or something to be overcome
yeah now that's kind of interesting
because i think in a lot of
systems there's this ideal that you
would find a very very quiet space and i
think that actually can really help a
lot
when you're beginning to meditate but
there is no
requisite
it's not like a part of the um
is not a part of the tool of shamatha
you know it it's different in that way
that yeah you could find yourself in
quite
noisy environment you'd still
apply the principle yeah
yeah and so your your sitting can have
sort of very different qualities at
different times and it can still be the
same
method yeah yeah radically it's uh
it's very it's it's a bit uh
it brings a bit of interest as opposed
to me because that was one thing
uh you know maintaining your awareness
kind of like
there has to be some sort of something
interesting in your experience
and that was i think some of my early
shamatha experiences like i knew what it
was supposed to be it was already
predefined
um and if it was going as planned it was
exactly the way it was
but it kind of got it was a little bit
hard to keep my
intention to stay with it because it was
it was not it was very
you know yeah this is what i thought it
was going to be now it's like a
surprising thing every time
something i'm really curious about is
whether um
whether you get more boredom in china
than you do in chalmetta
i you know i don't know because i'm
mostly coming from shinee
background but you know um
boredom has this kind of very particular
flavor
like it you know if you meditate for
long enough you're going to experience
boredom so i i sort of wonder whether
because of the focus and the
concentration and shamatha that you've
always got
something you know there's always
something there i kind of wonder whether
boredom is
less of a feature i don't know yeah yeah
for sure i mean because
for me at least especially in the
beginning chine was very boring um
yeah i needed without a technique it was
like what am i supposed to be doing here
you know like is the definition yeah
there's nothing to do well yeah a lot of
people coming to china i think they do
experience that
um you know what even is this it's like
what am i you know it's so
nebulous it's much much more nebulous as
a
as a practice than you know and it and
it's not systematized within itself in
the same way that
some shamatha practices so it's not like
there's this very um
clear clearly defined set of steps which
you can work through
which is you know that's very appealing
very appealing in some way
but it's really heading in quite quite a
different direction
and the experience that you have at the
end of that is going to be quite
quite different as well yeah well and i
i would say this also does kind of speak
to the fact that
um you know the the technique-heavy
stuff um
can be i think it's very common uh
especially with with broad teachings
um because you have to generalize and
and try and replicate a similar
environment so that people can
you know know where they're at uh where
so much more of
of the practice that i've been doing
ever since moving to more of roger on a
view
relies on getting feedback and and
yeah talking to people and getting
especially somebody who has more because
yeah it's so using your personal
life and circumstances and it's actually
working with
your personality and in some way
and you know personality is
very much personality and relationship
really are the path
aspects of buddhist tantra so
yeah yeah it's very different flavor in
that
in that sense yeah well
i'm kind of curious just to call to call
todd out todd did you
todd was a very experienced shamatha
practitioner
uh we practiced together in the past and
uh um
and you've moved to china recently uh
was boredom
part of your have you run into boredom
yet i don't know it's it's it's uh
you've had a different uh uh experience
starting chine than me which
speaks to the the how much variability
there can be
yeah i i i probably the opposite for me
actually i
i i feel like i went through
just terrible long long stretches of
boredom
in in shamatha and
it just it was interminable and uh
so i i feel like i kind of maybe beat it
out of me or something you know i get to
the point now where
i feel like i can find almost any aspect
of experience at least
moderately interesting so that's helped
a little bit with that with you name
yeah maybe boredom's just kind of par
for the course in
meditation yeah and one of my uh
earliest experiences of what they call
nepa
in the tibetan system which is um that
sort of very
clear uh um expansive spacious
bright sharp um grounded
experience that came through sticking
with boredom it was like
you know really really instant like
instantaneous sudden change of state
into mental clarity and it kind of felt
like i really remember it because it was
so
it was just so different to anything
else that i'd experienced at that time i
just remember this
you know i'm so i'm so bored i'm kind of
sleepy
and i'm just sticking with it and
sticking with it and it was like a veil
lifting somehow in terms of the mental
experience there
yeah and to put into context napa would
be the the fruit of
sheena prince of shinee practice yeah
that's that's correct
um i know we had a couple questions do
you want to take a look and see if
there's
what's been going on in the chat there's
just kind of a few things coming in here
uh there's a surf board there's a
surfboard
there's a surfboard there's no room in
surfboard okay
uh so with regard to the spelling of
sheena and sheena is
a transliteration
of the tibetan syllables
and there's no standard spelling of it
in the
arater spelling natural rinpoche uses
a graph accent
you can see it's spelled lots of
different ways uh you sometimes
see she nay n a y
phonetically um it's it's
the pronunciation is kind of shine nay
so yeah you know
um it's not like there's a correct way
and i will say to to even just kind of
come back to
charlie spending a bunch of time in the
beginning emphasizing
language um the intention of
this project is to move away uh
eventually from
a lot of the the more traditional and
language um and right yeah we haven't
gotten the name for china yet but we
have talked about it so
there's uh and yeah and i think in this
first
foundational series we'll be using
tibetan terminology we'll be using some
sanskrit
and beyond that we will have
um we'll probably step into it being
you know pretty much all english
i know i saw sarah had a good question
about the difference between remaining
and involved
and uh in a kind of disassociated
cool distance way of relating to the
situation
it was right below the technique or the
um
spelling question from lydia
hello sarah would you like to
to ask you your question or
so that we have it on the recording that
would be great thank you
yeah so when
i'm the remaining uninvolved
is i'm wanting to know more about like
the distinction between
that and um the kind of like
pop culture like distant cool like
dissociated and i can make a guess
of dissociation involves
protection armoring resistance to some
sensation and then you could remain
uninvolved with the resistance
and i i guess i want to feel
more connected to the remaining
uninvolved and i don't currently
quite feel that right
so yeah i see what you're you're getting
at there's this very
distinct difference between
renouncing rejecting um
having some sort of separation and
barrier and wall
there and the choice to remain
uninvolved which you know i was saying
about having this
always present potential for involvement
it's like uh
the connection is always there there's
there's still a connection when you
remain uninvolved
you see maybe so take an emotion
as an example so you feel the arising
emotion
so there are different choices that you
have when the sensation of the
emotion arises and you know there are
different things that you can
do in response and you could
you could just completely ignore that
push the sensation away
stop feeling the sensation you could
control that sensation so that it
subsides
that is that is not
what i'm referring to with remaining
uninvolved
remaining uninvolved doesn't get
involved in that kind of way
i mean you know if you're pushing the
pushing your sensation away you're
actively ignoring it you're actually
involved in some way you're just kind of
pretending not
you know you know what i mean so
you allow the sensation to arise and
choice is available if it's there
and if you're connected with that
sensation then choice is always
available
and the choice is maybe to not express
so you're feeling the sensation but
you're maybe not
um
showing and expressing that sensation
intentionally outward in connection with
other people
so you're remaining uninvolved with the
sensation but you still have a very
strong
connection with that sensation it's
still there
the potential to do all kinds of
whatever is there but you're just
letting it do its own thing
yeah letting the sensation do sensation
and
and mutate and and evolve
and do all kinds of things i mean the
way that we
get into these um habitual expression
or repression or you know
control of emotion or or
um
manipulation manipulation this this kind
of
projection of emotion onto everything
that's just as much um
you know that's kind of the flip side of
of repressing it
you know it's the it's the
giving full reign to that
quality of your experience um
so you know those are both involvement
in some way
so remaining uninvolved allows the
sensation of the emotion just to
stay around and be there um but
yeah yeah it's it's interesting for me
you know when i'm language is so hard
with chine because as as
i said it's it's very nebulous um
and yet like as i've practiced more and
more i've almost come to see that there
is a kind of
a flavor to involvement um
and involvement is you know well so so
even chine is the first of these four
practices that are
building up to zogen practice and
zogchen talks a lot about how
mind is always kind of manipulating
overlaying
judging uh putting things in reference
points
um it's always kind of it's an overlay
on your experience so it's always
manipulating the situation in some sense
um and when ordinary experience
ordinary experience yeah um and so and
and remaining uninvolved leads to this
this
uh the state this nepa eventually
um that it really just it there there is
no
categorization there's no preference
there's no judgment there's no
um agenda you know it's it's like it's
just allowing things to be very much
exactly the way they are yeah and i
haven't
i'm afraid to say that just because i
know that cliche is going to be
rife with you know letting things be as
they are being in the present but
i mean another way of saying it is just
allowing space
around whatever arises whether that's
internal or
in relationship you know not
having that kind of immediate need to
[Music]
uh yeah focusing
yeah right this is really important for
for practice as you know
the practice of the path in vajrayana
because you're
that is so much about involvement and
activity
and creating stuff and doing stuff and
you know enjoyment and everything that
in order for that to occur and mainta
and and occur in a way that is useful
and beneficial you actually need that
space you need to be really
familiar with it so that so that the
activity is
choice because otherwise it's just
habitual
you know you're just doing the same
thing and you can't actually see
you can't see those patterns you can't
see those
uh habitual ways of relating
because they're just you know they're so
automatic but having this
uh practice to begin with and
this familiarity with um
remaining uninvolved just means that
activity can occur in a very very
different
different way with a different kind of
quality
to the experience
thank you sarah tyler uh
ultimate you said you had a question to
further distinguish method and tool i
think that might be would you want to
ask your question sure so
um i was thinking about the the wrench
example um and in my mind it related to
i thought of hammering since i've done a
bunch of hammering
um and i was thinking about um
last summer when i was dealing with
wooden
um nails instead of
metal nails and that you know it was
basically the same sort of action but
there
still was a little bit of context
modification in there um
you know maybe not not as uh my
hammering had to be a little bit more
precise not as
high magnitude or what have you so it
sounds it sounds like
one of the differences you're pointing
to is sort of a spectrum
of the amount of context adaptation that
you need i think so
yeah okay yeah yeah since it seems like
in
almost any tool use there will be some
slight
um attention to context and modification
that's right
but then it it does feel like a
qualitatively different thing
to have sort of like context
modification be
the almost like the the entire flavor of
the activity you might say yeah
yeah that's very nicely put thank you
i've been you know i've been thinking
quite a bit how to
express the experience recently
the experience of the difference and
yeah i think you said that very nicely
um and i think also there's something
about the direction
in which you're heading with each of
these like
the the direction you're heading when
you're hammering is
you just get better and better at
hammering
and and sort of increasingly
able to be more precise
and i think something that
you get better at nebulosity the better
you get
at remaining uninvolved you get better
at the
indefinable um wiggly
sort of uh
gray areas somehow yeah yeah
and the direction you're heading is
expansive and
with the hammering the direction or you
know with meditation as a tool the
direction that you're heading
is really pretty specific
you know there are some very clearly
defined end goals
one of which is cessation right now it's
very simple
there's even quite a pretty distinct um
scoping of awareness that happens in
each one yeah
when i'm focusing like very narrow yeah
on on breath meditation for example
it feels like it's almost like going
infinitely
to a single point whereas other types of
more nebulous meditations feel like
they're entertaining more and more of my
environment
and eventually what you're doing in the
uh
the more shamatha oriented more what we
would
call sutrick approach is that you are
honing in so much that you get to a
point
where there's an explosion into
separate entirely separate uh
transcendence
if you like thank you
and that is very different that's very
very different from the
uh the approaches within vajrayana which
are
you're moving towards an experience
which
is is never going to be clearly defined
it will it's much more
about congruent activity in the moment
it's about relationship with the
what is arising in the moment
so there's it doesn't it doesn't lead to
a point of transcendence
it i would say maybe it leads to a point
or
not a point it doesn't lead to a point
it really leads to
a scope or a sphere of
um
fullness completeness complete
apprehension
congruent congruent apprehension it's
not like saying that you can have
perfect information
it's more um
full engaged presence in
life in the relationship with the
present moment yeah
and i guess appreciate it and and um
even
more of a kind of uh uh vajrayana thing
you know they they
vegetarian is so much defined on this
play between emptiness and form and so
the wholeness is the integration or
kind of yoking if we're yogi's of these
two
dynamics of the the pattern and the um
and the nebulosity
um and chine is quite you know it's not
the
this is a very the beginning of the base
the base
yeah it's it's the ground so we're going
to be looking at chine a lot in
in these series we'll kind of come back
to that as the uh
example of quite often
yeah so yeah gina is really getting a
real familiarity and comfort with
nebulosity so that then you can learn to
integrate and kind of
allow the form to yeah
and so it is kind of slightly artificial
as well
you know that's something that nat turn
rinpoche always i remember him saying
that
you know it's not an ordinary natural
state it is something that you are
intentionally cultivating
it's not um you know in sub 10 there's
this phrase the natural state
that's not um well it depends
what perspective you know it can be an
aspect of that but it is not
an ordinary everyday state it's
something that we
cultivate and become more familiar with
and then eventually it just kind of
arises
naturally in different circumstances
and i do think that i get the sense
especially from spending a lot of time
in the with the more
transcendent uh perspectives uh our
sutra
perspectives i think we we're thinking
transcendent might be a little bit more
broad uh ranging but yeah i think
transcendence is the
is the result isn't it or the intended
result in
that more sutured context you could say
yeah transcendence or yeah and and the
part of napa that
that would be um or that that's kind of
uh
the most uh constructed is that there is
no thought that's arising
when you're in this state and i think a
lot of other
transcendent uh uh approaches see that
as like that's the goal like that's when
everything's perfect is when there's no
thought anymore
uh things are just the way they are yeah
and i i can really see
how that happens as well and you know
it's such a nice state to be yeah
you know it's so
weird and clear and
lovely you know i think the the thing
that isn't um talked about a lot
is that there are different qualities of
thought-free
state and you can have this kind of very
very quiet calm
um almost like you're in a sort of
bubble
state and that is really very different
to this state nepa that we've been
talking about that is
you know it's thought free but it's
really bright i mean the
i always i always want to use this word
bright it's just
yeah very expansive it's still thought
free so there are these very different
mental
um mental states that
relate to different paths
yeah and and i even i think one of the
most emblematic things from a
traditional perspective
is just looking at like the the art from
very renunciative forms of buddhism
which is you know you always have the
the serene shaktimune buddha you know in
his
pleasant just like grin like oh
everything's fine and then all of a
sudden you're doing tantric
art and there's def you know and wrath
and
you know yeah that's a nice uh
yeah finding the the kind of um
the beauty in every aspect of our of our
personality
um yeah
i know we're we're getting close here
charlie did you want to start
orienting toward what we want to do in
the the group
uh breakouts or do you want to answer
any more a couple more questions
yeah other more questions let's take a
look and see if anybody else wants to
ask a question
because i'm sorry i haven't been paying
a lot of attention to the chat because
i'm really bad at multitasking basically
i've been on some um
some stoa type or zoom videos i just
so impressed by the way that some people
can just kind of
relate to the chat and still talk
lydia's very good at that
you're here lydia i can see you're in
the chat
yeah so does some other is there another
question in here
oh yeah we got we got a fair few uh
let's see here let me
um
maybe uh na rao
did you had a question on connection uh
finding presence of awareness
uh did you want to ask your question or
uh yeah sure i just wanted to like
clarify i guess
um so uh when you talk about remaining
uninvolved
would that be pretty much the same as
saying that you don't really
make a choice or choose to not make a
choice or like you
do not react to a phenomenon you're
aware of the possibility of a choice
yeah yeah so you're choosing the
uninvolved aspect so there is yeah
there's a choice
there's a choice there right and and the
second part
was uh you said that there is like a
connection
and uh i was wondering whether the
connection part is contained kind of
in the finding presence of awareness
part of the instructions so there is
still like presence of awareness and
this is what keeps you connected to like
you know what's happening
yep right yeah
good thank you yeah and the product
blending presence of awareness yeah
sorry jared that uh that is a phrase
that um i have
brought from context the arrow a phrase
that
nacho rinpoche uses in relation to um
going to be getting a little bit tibetan
here and zog chem practice of
sends in particularly which is um in
english he uses the phrase and kandra
chan uses the phrase um finding presence
of awareness
in the dimension of whatever
so in your in your shin a practice
you might start out by finding presence
of awareness in the dimension
of the breath and then you're actually
dropping that
so you're using that as a little bit of
a support
and then you drop that and eventually in
sheena practice the finding presence of
awareness
is in the
thought-free clarity
space of you know clarity and mental
experience or
the the experience of um
stuff arising in you know in terms of
body sensation
or noise outside or whatever
you'll eventually move into finding
presence of awareness
in the stuff which arises so that's
that's the follow-on
from sheena so that that potential is
always there in shinee but you're
allowing it to just be there does that
make some sense naruto
yeah yeah absolutely thank you so much
thanks for the question and
i'm actually kind of curious now i got a
question uh so
for for the presence of awareness is
this um
is this directly uh related to the empty
element of
the experiential
um yeah like the empty the empty aspect
of whatever is arising has to be
in contact with it right and we're
talking about an experience
here rather than you know a lot of like
2 000 years of buddhism is
arguing about emptiness and it's like
that yeah i guess we could say nebulas
what it is yeah nebulosity is it's it's
a really great
way of bringing the understanding that
you
and the qualitative understanding of
some
kind of emptiness and meditation
understanding that as
nebulosity in your daily activities is
one way to have a connection with your
meditation there
i did see one other uh question from
michael
uh this might be a quick one the thought
free state what is that
word thoughts or um so yeah
and this is yeah no it's anything that
arises in um
in in your mind
so it's ideation uh visual
stuff that comes up not so much talking
about bodily sensations so you allow
body sensation to be as it is and remain
uninvolved with that
and that can you know the more you
practice gna that does subside a little
bit and it sort of mutates
as well so it becomes sort of quite
pleasurable sometimes
um but you're mostly we're talking about
thought-free state
thought the tibetan word is nam tog
which is just stuff that arises
so whatever arises you remain uninvolved
with it
for the most part when you start
meditating and practicing that's going
to be
for most people that is thought
and then yes you become used to having
less
density of thought then
you begin to notice all the other kind
of stuff that
goes on and you know i sometimes wonder
i think
that what happens is that as the
the verbal density dissipates somewhat
it actually allows a bit more space for
other stuff to arise as well so they're
they're you know very
well documented well known phases that
people
do move through in meditation but i
don't want to say that these are
prescriptive
you know some people don't have a lot of
verbal
mental activity some people have an
awful lot of
uh visual or
yeah i'm just say awful it makes it
sound awful about
you know i didn't mean awful i mean it
was a rather british
phraseology i just you know i just mean
some people are more visually oriented
and again with in in vajrayana practice
you're
working with whatever the proclivity is
so you know if somebody
just individually what they
what they have going on in their mind is
a lot of very clear
bright visual stuff then you know maybe
yield on practice is going to be
a great practice for that person or you
know working with
the visual quality of things working
with
vision is going to be really useful and
helpful and you know other people are
more
somatically inclined or
yeah conceptually oriented or whatever
so you really kind of
work with personality in that way
thank you michael yeah
thank you
did we want to uh yeah i think it would
be a good time to start moving towards
the
outside i'm assuming we might go back to
get a little bit more on the method
uh uh or something yeah
um so really so the the breakouts
are for you to
explore the material that we've been
presenting here
in relation to your own lives and your
own practice
and you know maybe help each other
figure out
is this relevant is this not relevant
for me at the moment
how might this apply um you know just to
have a little exploration of that
material while it's still really fresh
and then you know if anything arises and
you have questions or
insights or anything that you want to
share we can come back
for a bit more of a larger group
discussion and exploration so should we
do that
now yeah i think so i had one quick
thing
this was something that came up but i
didn't get to mention it um
i thought it might be interesting
because maybe there's some people here
who don't
aren't meditating on a regular basis but
the interesting thing here is that
similar to what we covered in our last
stoa session
there is kind of a general technique or
method or view that gets employed in
informal ways throughout our life too so
this is one of the
the things that came to my mind was like
how we deal with our emotions
um you know maybe especially the ones
that are difficult
um did you you know i i thought maybe
the that we could make a little bit of a
correlation with with the method of
dealing with emotion in just day-to-day
life so that we could
so folks that don't have the meditation
background could talk about their
informal experience as well
yeah that's a great idea yep
yeah i mean basically you can talk about
whatever arises as well i mean
you know if there's something that is
going to be
um helpful regarding
employing vajrayana practice or whatever
and it's different then you know
follow that lead yeah gotcha okay
any any questions before we do break out
cool all right i will thanks michael bye
automatic three
four oops
fine there we go all right i'm going to
do automatic breakouts so this is going
to be random
since we have a fair amount of people so
uh yeah we'll see who you who you go
with
and then we'll we'll pull everyone back
here i'll give a couple minute warning
as we do
i will be probably at the right at the
90 minute mark
is anyone saying anything nope not yet
oh there we are i just wasn't sure
whether my sound had
disappeared
oh no no sound
so as everybody files back in um
probably did you want to just
do a quick uh closing here sign off for
the the stoa
listeners and and then uh maybe do some
reflection afterwards
right yes
we've had 90 minutes so far i think this
is a good point to finish the recording
and thank you very much to everybody who
has
been listening and contributing
and hello to future
hello and goodbye to future uh
audience great great yeah um
and yeah i just wanted to kind of
quickly thank peter uh and all of the
stewards of the stoa for creating this
space for us um
and uh and then a reminder too that the
stoil runs on a gift economy
um so if you're getting value of this
and you feel um
feel uh compelled to to donate or
uh anything like that you can go to the
stoa.ca and at the bottom there's a
gift link i believe it might be the
stowaway.ca gift
is the the correct place i'm not sure
but i want to make sure to always
uh say that and uh yeah thanks yeah we
were going to mention the
practice group as well if anybody who
has been listening
and wants to become engaged in
a community of practice or just wants to
kind of check that out
and um experiment with
adriana vue a little bit we have
a practice group that is unrecorded
that meets once a month at different
times to try to
um to include all of the different time
zones
um and we have a slack
group that is somewhat connected with
the practice group and you can join one
or
other of those are happy yogi's slack
um so
yeah if you're interested uh i guess the
the best way at this
moment uh would be to either reach out
to me directly
uh my email is me jaredjanes.com
um or you can dm me on twitter
uh charlie has a contact form on on
vajrayana
yeah my dms are open as well so great
um feel free to get in touch and there's
also a good chance that by the time
uh uh folks are listening to this replay
that you can go to evolvingground.org
um and that will should be able to point
you in a direction we don't have
anything there yet but it will
help gather the yogis
in the near future so thanks for guys uh
and yeah yeah we'll talk to you
next time at the next session all right